What were they trying to accomplish?
They were trying to get the attention of
the United States. They wanted a war.
They didn't understand us and come to
hate us. They have a very rudimentary
idea of who we are. People say, "Oh,
they they were making a political
statement, but the captured notebooks
tell us they really didn't know that
much about us." So, they had studied our
system, found a weak point, took
advantage of it. They looked at the
FAA's website and found the airports
with the largest number of security
violations. They did go to these flight
schools where chillingly they said they
didn't need to learn how to take off or
land. They just needed to know how to
operate the aircraft in the air. You
suddenly realize that your country is
crowded with heroes wearing ordinary
faces.
The British government wants to force
YouTube to downrank independent content
like ours and replace it with approved
messaging from the mainstream media. The
only way you can fight back and continue
to enjoy our content is to make sure
you're subscribed. Like this video and
comment below to have your say on what
the government is doing. Richard Miner,
welcome back to Trigonometry. We have
you here on the 25th anniversary of 9/11
which for those of us who lived through
was a moment of great tragedy. It was a
moment that changed the world. But more
importantly actually there is now a
whole generation maybe two generations
of people who don't even remember it
because they either weren't alive at all
or they were too young uh to really
understand the significance what of what
was going on. So on this day, what we
thought would be fantastic is to have
someone like you who's written a bunch
of New York Times bestsellers about
various aspects of this event uh to come
back on the show and talk to us about
actually the basics, the sort of cub
reporter questions, the what, when, why.
Um so welcome back again and uh let's
talk about it. What happened on 911
2001?
>> On the day itself 25 years ago today,
war plananes were hijacked and unlike
normal normal hijacking.
They did not communicate with the
outside world. They did not demand
ransom and instead they purposely flew
these planes into buildings on what
everyone describes as a clear perfect uh
Tuesday sky. it uh they crashed into the
um the towers um within 15 minutes each
other. Two jumbo jets uh collided with
the World Trade Center towers. Another
plane went into the Pentagon. Uh and we
have horrifying voice recordings of
people on the phone inside the plane as
it slams into the Pentagon. And then
there's the story of flight 93, the
fourth plane, which is hijacked
somewhere over Cleveland after having
left Maine and was believed headed
toward the US capital building itself.
If they had reached that target, roughly
5,000 people would have died, uh,
including members of the House and the
Senate and their key staffs, uh, other
dignitaries who were visiting on that
day. And the death toll would have been
much higher than in the World Trade
Center itself.
um 3,000 rough almost 3,000 people died
from more than a 100 countries. Um there
are conspiracy theories saying that the
Jews were warned in advance. In fact,
for the Orthodox Jews, there was a
religious holiday uh that they had been
following for thousands of years and
they stayed home on that day due to a
religious holiday, not due to any
advanced warning. But that is one of
those malicious internet rumors. But
let's not forget about the heroism of
the people on Flight 93 because it tells
us something distinctive about that day
and about Americans in general. When the
plane was seized by four hijackers over
Cleveland and redirected from its
intended destination of San Francisco uh
south towards uh south and east towards
the US capital. Uh immediately one
passenger was killed apparently
scuffling with the hijackers and the
rest were hurted to the back of the
plane and these ordinary Americans who
were encouraged to use their phones by
the hijackers because part of the
al-Qaeda plan al-Qaeda being the
terrorist group that had organized and
planned these attacks rehearsing them
for years by the way
uh wanted them to use the phones to
magnify the terror across the American
population to harness the social
networks of people who love those people
who are about to die to spread the sense
of terror and pain. But on those calls,
people didn't just talk, they also
listened. And they learned that other
planes had been hijacked. And because
they were uniquely American, these
ordinary people said when they were
herded to the back of the plane, "We
have to make a plan to retake this or
they will kill us and whoever we ram
this plane into." So they began boiling
water which is used in the back of the
plane to make coffee and tea. They began
assembling whatever they could for
weapons. We know just fragmentaryary
bits from the cockpit voice recorder and
from the transcripts of the phone calls.
And they attacked the hijackers. They
did not launch their attack until they
could see out the window. They were over
a rural area. They were aware there were
tons of aviation gas which would explode
and kill people on the ground. and they
wanted to spare as many civilians on the
ground as possible. Flight 93 is the
only flight in which no one on the
ground died.
Now, it's a heartbreaking story. They
did apparently, according to the
recordings, disabled two of the four
hijackers and were ramming the cart into
the cockpit door and may have gotten
inside the cockpit itself. There is
fragmentaryary last second recordings
where they're demanding that the they're
fighting over the controls of the plane
but from a flight of but from a height
of roughly 8,000 ft according to a small
plane that was observing them at the
time. They dived into the dirt killing
everyone aboard and there's a monument
for them now in near Shanksville,
Pennsylvania. But that is an incredible
example of people in real time making
decisions without any outside guidance
going against 40 years of conventional
wisdom. They were always instructed by
their bettererss.
Just cooperate with the hijackers. Be
peaceful. They will that's the best
chance of your survival is just to
cooperate with them. They fought them.
They ignored all the expert advice.
They made weapons. They made a plan.
They told the people that they loved,
that they love them, but that they had
to go. And we hear them uh on the
cockpit voice recorder. Those messages
are still clarified, classified, but
they are uh were played for the families
and I interviewed a number of the family
members uh several years after those
recordings. Uh but it's an extraordinary
story. One last detail of context here.
When I was on the Cash Lauda River in
Colorado, a boat ahead of me was
composed entirely of Japanese people and
the boat started to sink in the rapids.
And all the Japanese people turned to
the group leader and were waiting for
him to make a decision as the water
climbed up to their necks and eventually
over their heads before he dispersed
them to swim for their lives.
That might be how Japanese people react
in a crisis. Flight 93 tells us how
Americans act in a crisis. They ignore
the experts. They make a plan. They
consider all the ramifications. They
take great risks. And in the case of
flight 93, they came heartbreakingly
close to retaking that plane. They are
heroes,
Richard. And there were many stories of
heroism that day, of course, and we will
talk about all of them, including in New
York with the firefighters, with other
first responders. uh many of them gave
their lives uh like the people aboard
flight 93. But I I really think it's
very very important
for us to try and unpack the why because
of the way the world changed. Why did
this happen?
That's a big question. The short answer
is 1979.
In 1979,
in the Carter years of the American
presidency,
um through a series of missteps, there
was a revolution in Iran. An interesting
coalition of communists, Kurds, and
radical Islamists led by Ayatoll Kmeni,
who was in exile first in Iraq and then
in Paris,
uh flew back to Iran and was able to
launch an Islamic revolution in that
country.
What that did the the the revolution was
a Shia Islamic revolution but for Sunnis
outside Iran it was a watershed.
Suddenly it seemed like radical Islamic
utopia was possible that we saw
takeovers in Mecca in 1979
uh where the great mosque was taken and
for several months Saudi forces were
unable to retake it and many radical um
Muslims believed that Allah was
protecting the people holding the Grand
Mosque hostage. Ultimately, the Saudis
um under Prince Turkey alisel were able
to bring in French paratroopers who they
made all say the shahada converting to
Islam before they went in who cleared
out the the um the terrorists. But it
took months. Those two effects
turbocharged
um radical Islam from an idea that
existed among intellectuals and school
teachers and a handful of people inside
uh the Awan Muslim, the Muslim
Brotherhood and brought it out into the
realm of political possibility. And then
the third thing happens in 1979, the
Soviet invasion of Afghanistan. a
traditional Muslim country invaded by an
atheist communist superpower. And those
three things acting together
meant that jihad the preaching of
Abdullah Assam who was in 1979 a mentor
to Osama bin Laden that jihad is the way
and jihad does not mean spiritual change
in the thinking of Abdullah and in the
various Salafis who follow um
him and his his dogma his doctrine.
It means fighting on this earth and
killing infidels in order to bring about
the last days, the end of the world so
that Allah may reign supreme over all
the world and
they were cycle so to to spare
themselves revolutions like what they
saw in Iran across the Sunni Arab
countries. they began encouraging these
terrorists even in fact later in the
1980s uh opening their prisons and
sending these radicals to Afghanistan to
fight the Soviets. The thinking of Saudi
intelligence especially uh was that if
they die in Afghanistan, they're a holy
martyr and they're not our problem. Uh
and if they don't die, they will be busy
for a long time and not causing problems
here at home. This creates an
opportunity for a young scion of a
construction magnate named Osama bin
Laden. Osama bin Laden is forged by two
things in his life. In order to get his
father's attention as a young boy, he
had he did two things that stood out
among all of the other children.
Otherwise, most weeks of the year, he
was all but ignored. But on Friday after
Juma prayers he when his father would
gather with other adult men and 7 8
9year-old Osama would be summoned to
recite portions of the Quran from
memory. So he memorized the Quran as a
way to command attention and to get his
father's approval. This is the very
beginning before he gets introduced to
the radical philosophy of Abdullah Aam
and of the Muslim Brotherhood and of
other radical groups. And I don't want
to get down too many rabbit holes, but
al-Qaeda is not a direct descendant of
one thing, but the fusion of many
things. Uh the other the other way he
got his father's attention, and this is
important, is that for one, sometimes
two weeks a year, depending on the year,
the head of the family would take all of
the extended family, including young
Osama into the desert to live in tents
without human comforts.
And in this harsh environment, Osama
thrived. He loved the wild places. He
loved capturing and killing animals. Uh,
and while everyone else complained about
the lack of air conditioning, of cold
water, and so on, everyone wanted to
take a shower or a bath, he thrived and
he got his father's approval there. From
those two ingredients, once you add the
radical uh thinking of Abdullaham, Bin
Laden knew he had to get to Afghanistan
and create an opportunity for himself
because tens of thousands of radicals
were leaving jails, leaving mosques and
going to Afghanistan. So he created
something initially called al-Qaeda
suba, the secure base. And it was just a
place where you could as a fighter, a
jihadi fighter against the Soviets,
store your things, your watch, your
wallet and so on. And they began a paper
database. So uh base can also mean
database in in this form in this uh form
of garbage. Uh and he they made a
database of all of the fighters that
came through and whose belongings were
stored. Often they kept passports.
These passports would resurface by the
way on 911. So some of the people
believed to have died in the 1980s in
Afghanistan, their passports reappear
uh held perhaps by other people. Um
when they apply for visas to come to the
United States and go to flight school
and begin their more than a year of
operations inside the United States
before the 911 attacks. So, so bin Laden
ends up as a well-known figure in 1980s
Afghanistan. He has the names and
contact information for tens of
thousands of radicals, Muslims from the
Philippines, Bangladesh, India,
Pakistan, the Arab Gulf and so on. It is
an incredible advantage from which he
starts to build a terror network. At
first, he's just a financer. The very
first mention of Osama bin Laden in uh
US government documents is a state
department report from 1995
that says that refers to dismissive
dismissively that refers to bin Laden as
a moving bank.
But by the 90 but the State Department
was wrong by the '9s. He was organizing
and planning his own attacks. They spent
more than a decade planning and and
carrying out attacks against Americans.
Throughout the Clinton years, we saw
attacks on US a hotel in in Yemen that
was supposed to house US servicemen. We
saw attacks against the two two US
embassies in Africa simultaneously
within 8 minutes of each other and so
on. Right? So he's planning for 911. The
catalyst was a fellow named Holly Shake
Muhammad. He is like the independent
producer who brings the studio head bin
Laden the script and together they began
the plot and plan that leads to 911.
What were they trying to accomplish?
They were trying to get the attention of
the United States. They wanted a war.
Bin Laden had held press conferences in
Pakistan, in Bangladesh, and in other
places for many years openly declaring
war against the United States, using
those words. Um, and the United States
didn't respond. With 3,000 Americans
dead on the morning of September 11th,
America would have to resp.
>> In the leadup to 9/11, there were two
key attacks, it seems to me. One of them
was the first attack on the World Trade
Center in 1993,
and the other was the attack on SS Cole.
So let's talk about those very briefly
and how they paved the way for the
horrific offense on on 2001.
>> Sure. Uh so al-Qaeda launches attacks or
attempted attacks on the United States
or its interests every year from 1992 to
2001.
>> These attacks increase in sophistication
and lethality. The 1993 World Trade
Center bombing is carried out by a man
we now call Ramsey Ysef. Ramsey Ysef is
grows up with Hollik Muhammad uh in a in
a town outside of Kuwait City. Uh both
are not uh Kuwaiti citizens. They are in
fact because of their place of birth
permanently ineligible to become uh
Kuwaiti citizens. So they grew up they
and their families with secondass status
and the anger and frustration that that
implies because they were both high IQ
uh who people who did very well in
school the only place where they could
and to give you an idea of how low the
status was um during much of his
childhood palik Bahu's mother uh her
only source of living after the father
died suddenly um was to wash the female
bodies of the dead and be paid on a
perbot fee.
So this is a desperate precarious
existence with very low status despite
their high abilities. They do very well
in school but they are not given places
university will not be set aside for
them because those reserved primarily
for the Kuwaitis and for their foreign
uh visitors. the only place they can
find social advancement is inside the
various youth groups of the Muhammad of
the Muslim Brotherhood and but in
addition to so college Muhammad Anrren's
youth have become active in the theater
and singing troops of uh the Muslim
Brotherhood in near Kuwait city. uh the
college Muhammad himself is a gifted
performer and very popular uh and when
he goes to university in North Carolina
uh he's also popular for performing
skits and songs there right so this this
creative talent remains
um but they are frustrated and angry and
in the course of finding the social
outlet they embibbe the Muslim
Brotherhood's ideology and so in 1993
world chain center attacks
The plan is very simple. To take a truck
loaded with I forget how many pounds,
hundreds of pounds of explosive.
>> Mhm.
>> And to detonate it outside the wall of
the South Tower parking garage. MC You
does not care, but on the other side of
that small concrete block wall is a
woman who's 7 months pregnant named
Monica Smith. 7 months pregnant with a
boy, and she's eating her lunch. Another
person is behind another wall looking to
get uh to do an inventory count for a
restaurant that exists hundreds of feet
above them called Windows on the World.
They set the bomb. They try desperately
to leave the parking garage, but there's
a truck in front of them that is very
slow. They're blaring their horn and
they roar out onto West Street and make
their getaway just seconds before the
bomb explodes, killing Monica Smith. uh
and the workers on the world um
inventory counter uh waiter actually and
five other people. At first the US is
deeply confused by what happened. The
bomb is massive. It opens a crater that
is the mouth of the crater is more than
60 ft across and goes down nearly 100
ft. It drops concrete blocks into the
path of train station below. It severs
pipes. Uh so you have water and sewage
flow flowing into the crater. The
building is evacuated and one valuable
thing happens that is going to be
important on the morning of 911.
The New York City police and a separate
commission and panel by the legislators
in Albany, which is the state capital of
New York, study the evacuation plan, all
the problems that went wrong. And so
they change how the wood twin towers are
to be evacuated. How the lights, there
were no lights in 1993 in the stairway.
As soon as the power was cut, the
stairways were dark and therefore people
moved down those staircases much more
slowly.
Thanks to that attack
um the on 911, most of those lights were
battery powered and so when the power
went out, people could still evacuate
close. So if and those lines moved much
more quickly. There were many many other
changes made. But as a result 3,000
people died on 911.
>> And Richard, sorry to interrupt, but
what what was their fascination with the
World Trade Center?
>> That's a really interesting question,
Francis.
When you go through so at the combating
terrorism center at West Point, they
have about two and a half million pages
worth of captured documents from
al-Qaeda.
uh and those have been translated into
English mainly by the US army or by US
other government
>> and uh the FBI separately translated the
notebooks left behind in the rental cars
of the hijackers. They drove rental cars
to the airports where they launched the
hijackers.
Um
and so two things come from that. One is
they thought that the World Trade Center
was literally the center of world trade.
They thought if they blew it up, all
global trade would come to a stop. It
never occurred to them that property
developers created a marketing name,
World Trade Center. And in fact, there
are other World Trade Centers in the
United States, right? Um, and it's it's
kind of those things that's about as
meaningful as the term international
airport, right? The the small town
airports in the US that have one flight
a week to Canada, but it's an
international airport, right? Um, and
they also, another thing that comes of
this is people say, "Oh, they they were
making a political statement, but the
captured notebooks tell us they really
didn't know that much about us." So, one
of the notebooks left behind uh with the
hijackers is a lengthy uh description on
page one of the notebook of the
difference between shampoo and
conditioner.
>> Right? So, these were not this was not a
detailed political protest. They wanted
to attract the attention of the great
Satan, the United States, and go to war
with it and hopefully to triumph over
it. This is a battle in their mind. It
wasn't really about something the United
States did.
>> So, they wanted to drag America into a
war, which they wanted to win.
That was the the purpose of all of this.
>> Yes. The story in their head is we
defeated the Soviets. Now, in reality,
the jihadi forces from the Arab
countries had very little impact on the
Soviets, right? We can point to one or
two battles in which they may have
played a an important role. Mostly they
didn't join the main war effort. Uh they
did random terror attacks. Um one fun
aspect of this is they didn't just have
car bombs. They had camel bombs where
they put bombs on camels and had them
explode in marketplaces.
Um, most of the war fighting which
actually did drive the Soviets out was
carried out by Afghans themselves. And
so an important detail here which many
people miss is while the Saudis and
other Gulf Arabs funded the jihadis, the
US did not. The US never funded
al-Qaeda. I talked to every living CIA
station chief responsible for
Afghanistan and many other officials and
the record on this is overwhelming. The
US never supported al-Qaeda or bin Laden
himself or for that matter any Arab
jihadis. They supported pushons
uh and other groups which later became
known as the Northern Alliance. Um, and
that's who they were, the people who are
doing the bulk of the fighting. But
nonetheless, in the mind of the jihadis,
they defeated the one superpower, the
Soviets. With 9/11, they're expecting
another battle and they would defeat the
other superpower, America, and that
would make them the best in the world,
and they hope bring about the end times
and uh lead to the end of the world and
Allah triumphant.
And that being the case, what about the
SS Cole, how what was the impact of that
and what was the significance of that
particular attack?
>> So from the 1993 World Trade Center
bombing, there were a series of attacks.
There's an attempted assassination of
the Pope. There's planned assassinations
of Bill Clinton. There's a foiled plot
called Ojinka uh that was going to start
out of Manila where they hijack 11
planes over the Pacific. that was foiled
uh by a very enterprising u Filipino uh
police chief uh who was pregnant and in
flip-flops when she arrests uh Ramsay
Ysef's co-conspirator.
Uh that's a whole other wonderful story.
Um and so these these attacks escalate.
There are attacks on two US embassies in
uh in Dar Salam, Tanzania and in
Nairobia.
Um and then the the climax of the
Clinton years from an al-Qaeda
perspective is the attack on the USS
Cole. Uh they had attempted an earlier
attack on the USS the Sullivanss. Uh
that ship is named after five brothers
who died on the same ship in uh in World
War II uh and fighting the Japanese. And
it is um
but their attack fails because their
boat sinks before it reaches the target.
They adapt very quickly and they launch
an attack on the USS Cole. And what we
have is the first time a US Navy ship is
in danger of sinking and total loss
since World War II. They blow a hole
that I think is 40 feet in the uh wide
in the side of the hole. And only
through the heroic efforts of the
captain and the crew. By the way, dozens
are killed and injured. Uh through
pumping a three-day roundthe-clock
effort are they able to save the ship uh
get it to port and safely evacuate. And
the ship itself still a flood today.
heavily. Uh Bin Laden does not hide his
involvement. He writes a poem glorifying
the attack which is widely published. Uh
and there are phone calls linking uh the
the various people who carried out the
attack uh both in Yemen uh and to their
pay masters in parts of Africa and calls
to Afghanistan. We have a complete chain
of evidence uh of Bin Laden to the
attack on US skull which is the largest
attack on a US warship since World War
II.
>> Uh Richard, sorry uh just going back a
little bit. I was so shocked by what you
said about because in my in I I you will
be aware that in the wake of 9/11 and
frankly prior to that that the universal
belief was that America had created uh
the al-Qaeda by funding it the stingers
and all of that. So, not that I don't
trust you, you know how much we love you
on the show, but I went on Venice and
had a quick look and it says that US
funds did not go directly to Bin Laden,
but they did go to native Afghan
mujahedin commanders
uh who were part of the movement that
then became al-Qaeda. Is that accurate?
>> The first part of it is absolutely
accurate. So, um there was an explicit
deal and this is not secret. This was
reported on the front page of the
Washington Post in 1986, right? An
explicit deal, dollar for-dollar
matching, the Reagan administration
would spend up to $1 billion, and they
did um funding native Afghans and the
Saudis would spend up to $1 billion
funding the Arab uh holy warriors, if
you will. These are separate groups of
people. They speak different languages.
They have different beliefs uh and they
have different aims for the future of
Afghanistan.
Um the
the idea that the CIA funded bin Laden
is an attempt to conflate a very broad
movement with very different groups in
it as lump it all as one thing and say
we funded that one thing therefore and
bin Laden. That is just not the case.
And in fact,
>> so just for clarity,
>> just for clarity, what you're saying is
the US funded people who were fighting
the Soviets, but not bin Laden and not
the foreigners who came to Afghanistan
to fight the Soviets. That's what you're
saying.
>> That's right. Funded by the Saudis and
by the Gulf. And in fact, the whole time
of the 1980s, Bin Laden is openly
anti-American
um and says so. And uh there was a me,
it's in my book, Losing Bin Laden, there
was a member of Congress visiting
Afghanistan and he was told to stay away
from these bin Laden camps that they
were hiking around because if Bin Laden
captures him, he will torture and kill
him. So this is not somebody on the CIA
payroll.
>> Fascinating.
>> There's much more evidence if you want
to talk about this in detail. There's
much much more evidence. Um, but also
think about it from the CIA's point of
view, right? A bunch of ideologically
driven, ill-trained foreigners are not
an ideal indigenous force to fight the
Soviets. The people who are fighting for
their native lands, who speak local
languages, whose political goal is
simply to drive the Soviets out, not to
create a religious utopia. Those people
are much easier to work with, far more
controllable, and far better trained.
They'd been in combat for decades.
Remember Afghanistan had a civil war uh
following the departure of the king in
the 1970s um where native Afghans were
fighting communists, right? And then
when it looked like they were going to
succeed in driving the communists from
power, the Soviet Union intervened to
save their ideological allies rolling
tanks across the Oxis Bridge on
Christmas Eve 1979. So these people had
been fighting Soviets and communists for
decades. They had organized training
regimens, uh, command structures. Um,
they were focused on the objective the
CIA cared about. CIA did not care about
trying to create a religious Muslim
utopia in Afghanistan.
Not only that, but al-Qaeda was and and
the other Arab jihadis were very hard to
control. most of their attacks were on
other Muslims, not on um Soviets
themselves. Uh and for example, look at
what is now called Nurstan, what used to
be called Kafiran and a region in
Afghanistan.
Kafiran means land of the unbelievers.
>> And these people did not start to
convert to Islam until the 1960s.
And by the time the radicals arrived in
the 1980s, maybe 5%, maybe 10%, I mean,
there's no good census data here, uh,
were Muslim, but through war and
conquest, uh, they wanted to convert
them to Islam. A lot of bin Laden and
the associated Arab terrorist groups
were attacks against these tribal people
in what was called once Kafiran is now
known as Nurstan, land of light, because
they did succeed in
in converting the majority of them.
Right? So that's the ideological and
targeting focus of the Arabs was on the
Afghans who were not following their
form of Islam.
The native Afghans who the CIA was
funding, their goal was getting rid of
the Soviets, which was the US foreign
policy goal. So it would have been
pointless to fund these groups. They're
hard to control, hard to manage, ill
trained, and don't share your
objectives. And on top of all that, they
want to kill you if you're a CIA
official, right? So, it just
operationally makes no sense. But when I
talked to uh Beard, who is one of the
CIA, I talked to every living CIA
station chief for Afghanistan who served
between 1980 and 1992. Right now, you
could say, "Okay, these are
self-interested, fine." But no one else
would track them down and talk to them.
And there was just they laid out in very
clear non- ideological non-defensive
terms. There's just we had no orders to
fund these people. We had no money to
fund these people. We had no desire to
fund these people. And these people were
trying to kill us.
>> So you don't write checks to people who
are trying to kill you.
>> That makes sense. Did the people that
they funded then with many of them part
of the Taliban?
>> No. The Taliban are created much later.
The trial are born in 1994.
So remember the
>> what I mean is did they become the
Taliban? Sorry to interrupt again.
>> The mujahedin did not become the
Taliban. The Taliban is um created
mainly by Pakistani intelligence
services, the ISI, uh and a bunch of um
local Islamic teachers. They're trying
to get the Taliban were trying to impose
the severe version of the official
version of Islam according to Pakistan.
Um, and later the so-called mujaheden,
the Arab foreign fighters ally
themselves with the Taliban because the
Taliban are not strong enough on their
own. Um, but the USbacked forces become
known as the Northern Alliance. And if
you remember, two days before 911 on
September 9th, the head of the Northern
Alliance is murdered by an al-Qaeda cell
posing as a Belgian camera crew. They
have a bomb inside the camera and it
detonates. That's how Massud, the leader
of the Northern Alliance, is killed on
September 9th. So they saw the Northern
Alliance as the enemy. The Taliban is
something that's created later. It's
driven by different causes and different
flows of money. But the muja do ally
with it not in 94 but after. Remember
there's a whole group a whole galaxy of
these groups in Afghanistan Pakistan and
people move between groups. Um we have
captured documents that show that people
get frustrated that their martyrdom
opportunity is delayed. It's like Lakshi
Taiba for example which is one of these
groups and they'll move to ISIS. Their
martyrdom opportunity is further delayed
there. So they shift to al-Qaeda. Like
they're moving around, right? And
they're looking for
they're looking to die and therefore
change their status in their community.
>> Like most people, I want more energy,
better focus, and to still be sharp and
strong years from now. But every time
I've gone in for my annual checkup, it's
the same thing. Wait weeks to get an
appointment, sit in a waiting room, and
then you're in and out in 10 minutes.
Everything looks fine, they say. Drink
more water, sleep a bit more. No real
insight, no plan, just vibes. That's why
every time I visit the US, I use
superpower. Members get 150 plus
biomarkers tested every year across two
separate tests. One to set your baseline
and one later to see what's actually
changed. That's a different category
information to what you get standing in
a doctor's office once a year. It covers
heart, liver, thyroid, hormones,
metabolism, vitamins and mineral levels,
gut health, and even environmental
toxins. Superpower turns all of that
into a personalized health plan rather
than a print out you never look at
again. Members using it are catching
early risk factors for disease that a
standard checkup would have missed
entirely. Take control of your health
with Superpower. For a limited time, our
listeners and viewers get $50 off their
membership at
superpower.com/trigonometry.
That's superpower.com/trigonometry
for 50 bucks off your Superpower
membership. And after you sign up,
they'll ask you how you heard about
Superpower. Tell them trigonometry sent
you to support the show. And Richard, we
can see looking back at the events over
the '9s. There's a clear trajectory
happening here. The attacks were
escalating. They were not only
escalating, but they were becoming more
frequent. They were attacking US soil.
They were attacking US Navy. They were
also attacking embassies.
Why was there someone not in government
raising the alarm going, "Look, we need
to do something here. This is serious
and it's going to be inevitable that
there's going to be another Islamist
terrorist attack on our soil."
>> Well, the danger to be fair to the
Clinton administration, right, we can
look back from our point in time and say
it was obvious this was going to happen,
but for people who are living in the
moment, it isn't clear. So, I talked to
uh both of Clinton's uh national
security adviserss and Tony Lake, who
was uh the national security adviser in
in the early Clinton years, says that he
he received his first briefing on
al-Qaeda sometime in 1994.
This is years after the attacks have
begun. This is year after the World
Trade Center bombing. At this point,
they hadn't linked uh the World Trade
Center bombing to al-Qaeda.
>> Um, and
he said he wasn't sure if he mentioned
it to the president or not. Uh, maybe he
thinks the first conversation with
President Clinton about al-Qaeda was
sometime in 1995, right? Why is he hazy
about this? He's not being defensive.
A lot's going on. And at the time this
didn't seem among all the various
threats they're facing the most
important right um the timeline becomes
a lot clearer and a lot more definite
and we see a lot more reports in the
late 90s but in the early 90s remember
when the World Trade Center explodes and
the FBI is called in they're trying to
figure out what if this was a work of
terrorism in the beginning they're not
even the first few hours they're not
even door, right? They change the name
of the investigation to trade bomb only
when they get enough bomb residue out of
the crater to say, "Okay, this was
definitely a bomb." Right? Uh so that
happens
five, six hours into the investigation,
but for days they're like, "Is this a
Yugoslav terrorist group? Is this uh
far-right extremist from, you know,
white nationalists from the United
States? Is this Nobody knows, right?"
And uh even after the initial arrests
and that's a whole interesting story or
they unwind the plot where the guy has
returned to get the rental car um so he
can get the deposit back and use the
money to buy a flight to escape because
the ticket that Muhammad Ata the ring
leader has given him is not a real
airline ticket. It's a child's ticket.
He has to upgrade it or to get on a
flight back to Pakistan. And um
you know this they it takes them months
to put the pieces together about that
bombing itself connecting it to a larger
global narrative doesn't really cohhere
into anything until the middle of 1995
at the earliest.
Um, and that's also why when Sudan
offered to arrest Bin Laden and turn him
over
>> uh to the States, that wasn't seen as
that high a priority either. Now,
Francis, to your point, were there
mid-level people who were specialists
saying, "This is a major problem. This
is very important. You need to do
something." Absolutely.
But again, in fairness to the Clinton
administration,
these people, all all these specialists
think their specialty is the most
important thing,
>> right?
>> They're all with their hair, right? So,
how do you as the politically elected or
politically appointed decision maker say
I should listen to expert 132 and ignore
all the others? Right? It's it's
difficult, right? Another problem here
is the government is very siloed. This
is something the 911 commission report
pointed out in great detail. So when I
talked to then CI the Clinton's first
CIA director, James Wolsey just died
recently. Um Woolseie wanted information
that the FBI was gathering uh because it
has obvious implications for CIA
investigations. And the FBI refused to
share because he says, "Well, you'll
mess up our case, right? The the FBI was
completely focused on launching a
criminal case. And so, if we share any
evidence with you, we have to share it
with uh the defense and we'll have to
give up all our sources and methods to
defense. So, when you want these
documents, you can have them when we
present them at trial, which turned out
to be in the middle of 1996."
Woosey also begged for translators. Less
than 10% of the phone intercepts coming
out of the Middle East were being
translated and CIA wanted more
translators
and um
because Woolseie had committed a
political offense unknowingly, right? He
had he was told um by Bruce Lindseay in
the White House that they want to
replace the general counsel of the CIA
with a friend of Bill a president
someone who had supported the president
in his election efforts
and Woosey said no we have a very
capable general counsel now there's no
reason to replace her uh or him I can't
remember but uh and as soon is he did
that. He was shut out of all meetings
with the president. So, he never got to
meet with the president one-on-one. He
was in the room with crowds of other
people and a few handful of occasions.
To try to get the president's attention,
he would go with the CIA daily briefer
and sit outside the president's office,
but he can't just walk in
>> and was never asked inside. So, he never
got to present his case to the president
about al-Qaeda.
he was never able to get the president
to force the FBI to share its
information.
Uh and the FBI didn't translate things
unless it had a direct what they thought
a direct bearing on the case.
>> So example uh in earlier before the
World Trade Center bombing there had
been a killing of a Jewish leader named
Meer Kahan and those uh documents were
not translated for 8 10 years. when they
were they showed you that the the very
infrastructure used by the people and
the places by Ramsey Ysef were the same.
Uh but they didn't want to spend the
money to translate the Arabic. So there
were translation problems, there were
bureaucratic infighting, there were
silos, and then there were political
gains. Uh, and if al-Qaeda was seen as a
real existential threat, all of those
things would have been pushed aside by
the force of the executive. But because
it wasn't seen that way, those things
weren't pushed aside.
And also we had people like Khaled Shake
Muhammad who was in college during the
'9s in the United States who was a
literal enemy on home soil.
And when you look at that, you think to
yourself,
I guess the question is,
could it have been prevented? Could we
have caught KSM earlier? And how many
times was he able to slip through the
net?
>> Oh wow. Yeah. Well, there's a famous
case in 1995 where uh the FBI misses him
by hours out of a safe house in uh and I
think Qatar because the Qatari uh
minister I think of religious
instruction. Anyway, one of the
ministers warns uh you know college
Muhammad that the US is coming for him.
Um well let's go back to uh the
schooling in North Carolina of College
Shake Muhammad the architect of 911.
So when you talk to his family in Kuwait
and other places
and his school teachers they will tell
you that he was a normal kid who got
radicalized in the United States. And
there actually is pretty good evidence
for this. Yes, he was coming out of the
youth groups of the Muslim Brotherhood
in Kuwait and the school didn't
cooperate very well on this, but there
appears to have been a Muslim
Brotherhood scholarship uh paid
for his schooling in the United States.
But the US, especially before 911, but
even now, doesn't really do background
checks of the foreign students debts.
So um
and sometimes the foreign students it
admits are less qualified than the US
students they could have admitted in
their place um because they're trying to
meet at this time period certain racial
or ethnic quotas. Right? So Khali Shikh
Muhammad would not have been admitted if
he had to compete openly because his
English at that stage was very poor. Uh
and his knowledge of engineering which
he said he was going to study wasn't
very good either. Um so he would not
have been a normal candidate except the
they were trying to tick certain boxes
and he came with scholarship money from
abroad which is high margin for the
university.
Um so clearly additional regulations
need to be applied on the admissions of
foreign students and on what basis and
so on right I think the US should
educate the highest IQ the most capable
foreign student in the world without
question we should attract them and
train them and teach them
>> but the second thing we need to think
about
is the social dynamics
so he he went to two different
universities in the United
um one of them is was avowedly
Christian. He felt isolated
um and so he gravitated toward other
people whose language he was isolated by
language, right? His English just was
>> at stage very poor. So he sought out
other Arabic speakers who were far more
radical than himself
and he fell into a group of them where
in order to maintain his friendships he
had to share their ideological
commitments. So it's a lot like a guy
joining a group because there's a hot
guy or hot girl in it and he will just
conform his beliefs in order to be this
person. In his case, he desperately
needed a social outlet and not to feel
isolated. And so when Halik Muhammad's
family members say, you know, hey, he he
was going to discos and picking up girls
in Kuwait, he comes back and he's a
Salafi. He's very strict. He uh he
doesn't, you know, many changes in his
personal life. This was and they blame
the United States. Well, really the
culprit here is the social network at
the university of other foreign
students. And in order to survive in
that very small ecosystem of 20 25
Arabic speakers, he had to conform. And
ultimately he becomes a kind of leader
among them because he overconforms
uh and um they get in trouble for uh
slaughtering a goat in a baseball dugout
in the university so that they can eat
in a certain ritualistic way and so on,
right? But he he becomes increasingly
militant because this binds the group to
him and makes him feel less alone. So
when we admit people into our
universities who lack the language and
social skills to connect, we we're
setting up a dangerous situation where
they will go to other people and you get
an island of misfit toys. Now most of
the time these are just um you know sad
train spotters but in other cases the
social dynamics there create a toxic
environment that makes all of them or
many of them into radicals. Uh I talked
to an imam leader who was a student um
and he now runs several mosques in
Greensboro, North Carolina
who was a student with College Chick
Muhammad and um he openly said he loved
him. He was um but he thought that this
political activity was a distraction,
right? uh that they were constantly
focused on um trying to have a political
outcome rather than getting people to
really understand and know Islam. Now
that's his reflection
5 10 years after 9/11. Um but I thought
it was fascinating. What I was going to
ask you, Richard, is um you we've talked
about the ideology. These people want to
start a war with the United States, but
you're describing the mastermind
KSM, and it sounds like a bit of a
loser.
You've got Osama bin Laden over there in
Afghanistan. How do these people I mean
you're not when I think about an
organization that's capable of hijacking
four planes, flying them into buildings,
which is, as I understand, not
particularly easy thing to do if you
haven't been a pilot for many, many
years.
>> How do you get this bunch of misfit toys
committing
probably the greatest terrorist atrocity
in human history with a high level of
sophistication? And for context, Khaled
Shake Muhammad's nickname was KFC
because of his prediliction for it. And
he was weighed over 200 lb. So it's not
like he was a physical specimen either.
>> Well, he becomes fatter living in
Pakistan. Yeah. Right. In the 90s he was
known as the brain. His nickname KFC is
after uh 911.
>> So he's smart.
>> Uh yes. Uh, and look, if he had there
had been a path to citizenship for him
and his family in Kuwait, we may never
have heard of him, right? He he may have
become an engineer in the oil fields or
done something else. Uh, we will never
know. However, um, to get to your
question,
people become terrorists because it
solves an important problem in their
life. Either meaning or isolation.
They're trying to solve for social
isolation or they're trying to solve for
meaning, for purpose.
Terrorism gives you a purpose.
But to carry out that purpose, you need
money. Um because it's not easy to get
people into you got to get visas to you
got to recruit people. You have to get
visas to get them to the United States.
You need to get them into pilot school.
They need to live somewhere. They need
to eat something. any clothes, etc. So,
you need venture capital, right? Bin
Laden had a lot of that.
Um, and college chick Muhammad
tried to sell many different plans to
bin Laden.
>> He gets to meet Bin Laden by playing on
his family connection to Ramsey Ysef,
>> who bin Laden admired and who had
carried out the 1993 World Trade Center
bomb. So once he forges a connection
with bin Laden and his inner circle, he
is pitching various plans and the plans
are refined repeatedly. Uh so the
earlier plans were simultaneously
hijacking eight aircraft, four on the
west coast and four on the east coast
with targets in San Francisco and Los
Angeles and so on.
>> Uh they pruned that out of the plan.
It's just too operationally difficult.
four is when they think the largest
number of planes they can hijack
>> without a US response.
But it's it's very much like I hate to
keep going back to the Hollywood
comparison, but it's very much like an
independent producer with a very
promising script having to negotiate
with a studio for financing and
distribution. Right? So, he needed um
al-Qaeda's money. He needed al-Qaeda's
ability to forge documents and to move
people um in secure ways. He needed
secure communication. He needed a lot of
resources beyond money. Um and to do
that he had to compromise with them. Uh
and they unfortunately made the plan far
more practical. Um but bin Laden was
just desperate for his war in his mind.
And this is in his writings. This is not
a theory of mine. Uh they had defeated
the Soviets even though in reality the
jihadis had virtually no impact on the
Soviets except for you can maybe give
them two battles. The pivotal roles in
two battles maybe. Um but in Bin Laden's
mind they driven out the Soviets. They'd
beaten one superpower. They wanted to
beat the other. They thought if they
could force the United States to come to
the mountains of Afghanistan to meet
them that they would crush them.
And that didn't happen. When the US did
deploy to Afghanistan,
um the military studies this of course
they look at the number of time how how
many minutes a firefight lasts.
Uh and those times got shorter and
shorter because the US got increasingly
efficient at killing them. And there
there is a major battle in 2002 or 2003
Shamali planes it's called in which they
fielded
hundreds maybe close to a thousand
fighters against um a US unit a much
much smaller US unit and were utterly
defeated and never tried a massed battle
again.
So um this fantasy of bin Laden that
said if we can force them to come and
fight in in Afghanistan we can beat them
like we beat the Soviets
>> is just probably false. But in 9 before
911 of course bin Laden had no way of
knowing that. He thought if anything the
Americans were softer and easier to
beat.
>> Um and
>> and what was the logistics of the
operation? Richard, tell us how how do
these just random guys from the Middle
East get to the point where they know
how to fly a plane? They know how to
hijack a plane. How do they hijack a
plane? All or tell us the mechanics.
>> Okay. So, why are so many of the 19
hijackers Saudis? This doesn't mean the
Saudis hate us. It means that there was
a special program that the State
Department had launched due to political
pressure to speed up the visas for Saudi
citizens. So, for example, uh if you
were Britain or France in this time
period, you had visa waiver access into
the United States. You didn't need a
visa at all, right? You just say, "Here
it is. See, see the passport. Let me
in." And um
the Saudis wanted that, but of course
that was never going to happen because
in the '9s the risk of people from Saudi
was well known. um and from that region
in general. It wasn't an anti-Saudi
bias. It's just an awareness. Um look,
the there's the same reason why, you
know, there are certain geographies that
present geopolitical risk, let's say,
that say France, Germany, Britain,
Denmark don't, right? Uh so to
compromise with the Saudis they created
uh visa express which was a a very quick
system for getting a US visa. So for the
Saudis it was a matter of prestige. They
wanted to be treated like the Europeans
and Australians. Uh and this was the
compromise. As a result the people who
became the hijackers were able to get to
take advantage of this program. If this
program had been offered in Qatar
instead of Saudi Arabia, 19 of the
hijackers would have been from Qatar,
not Saudi, right? So, they had studied
our system, found a weak point, took
advantage of it.
How did they select the airports where
the planes were going to leave? They
looked at the FAA's website
um and found the airports with the
largest number of security violations.
They knew that Logan Airport in Boston,
for example, was run by a political
appointee who had previously been the
chauffeur for the governor of
Massachusetts. So they thought they
picked airports. Uh Dallas airport in
Washington, for example, was another
where there were a long history of
documented security lapses. So they used
US government data publicly available in
a free society. It's how we work to plot
where to hijack, which planes to hijack.
They needed planes that were going to
travel the full length of the continent
of the United States because they would
have the most tons of fuel on board and
therefore have the greatest explosive
capacity.
>> So you wanted um aircraft that were
fully loaded that were coming from
airports that were had weak security
procedures and the ring leader Muhammad
flew out of a small airport in Maine and
then changed planes to join a flight I
believe out of Logan.
memories on that uh because they also
thought that that flight uh would be
easier for them to get into the system.
Uh
and the woman who gave him his ticket
testified that later that she thought he
was a terrorist but didn't want to
discriminate against him or be
unwelcoming. So they knew this factor as
well. They took advantage of existing
American weaknesses to exploit
a system that they wanted to destroy.
>> And didn't they also classify the
terrorists into which ones were going to
be the ones flying and which ones were
going to be the muscle?
>> Right. Not all of them went to pilot
school. Very few did.
So there was at least two muscle on the
plane. They were meant to control the
passengers. And then there was a pilot
and a co-pilot who had received some
pilot training. Um, the reason why we
have so much transponder data is it took
them a long time to figure out how to
turn off the transponder. Their training
wasn't that good and know what all of
the the
controls did on the aircraft.
>> Is that American 11 trying to call?
>> We have some planes
on returning to the airport.
And who's trying to call me here?
>> American 11, are you trying to call?
>> Nobody move.
>> Everything is okay. If you try to make
any move, listen to yourself and the
airplane. Let's stay quiet.
>> That's good. I thought you were
representing the move.
>> Nobody move.
going back to the airport.
Don't try to make any stupid
1523. Did you hear your company? Did you
hear some interference on the frequency
couple minutes ago screaming?
>> Yes, I did. 797 and uh we couldn't tell
what it was either.
>> Good night. Cleveland, if you hear the
sound
remaining, we have
captain. I would like to always remain
seated on board and are going back to
the airport and our demand. So please
remain quiet. But also there's there was
a culture of casualness among security.
Most cockpits were not locked. Um and on
the case of flight 9 93, the airline,
United Airlines actually required in its
regulation, internal regulations that
the keys for the cockpit door be kept in
an unlockable cabinet right next to the
cockpit door. So the stewardist could
just this cabinet grab the keys and and
get into the cockpit to uh to deliver
coffee or whatever you um one thing most
people may not understand at this time
period, right? Um
the flight attendants would be going in
and out of the cockpit pretty routinely.
Um
>> not just bringing meals and coffee, but
depending on the rules set by the
captain uh in this time period, you
pilots could smoke in the cockpit. And
so one or more of the flight attendants
might pop into the uh cockpit on a long
flight to catch a smoke if the captain
allowed smoking in the cockpit. In that
time period, union rules and aviation
rules allowed them to do that. So they
were constantly moving in and out of the
cockpit. Earlier um cockpits used to be
wide open and in fact children rounded
up once the plane had had leveled off
and brought into the cockpit to meet the
pilot and say hi and and look out the
pilot's window. Right. So it was a that
that now I'm describing the 70s and 80s
earlier time. Uh, and some airlines give
out little children's wings where after
they visited the cockpit, they would pin
it on their shirt and, you know, it was
it was marketing, but it was, you know,
a great life experience for certain kids
at a certain time period. So, it was
still fairly casual like that. Um,
>> and the captain would come out of the
cockpit from time to time in this in the
90s and sometimes talk to the passengers
in first class or uh get something out
of his bag or what have you. So it
wasn't a hardened um place. And so it
was even though there had been
hijackings since the late 1960s in the
United States and in the Middle East and
in Europe,
they really hadn't changed the system
from this much more casual trusting uh
system that emerged in the 50s and 60s.
And Richard, didn't they use small
blades which were allowed by airports
and airport security to actually take
over the planes once they were airborne?
Oh, so this is very tricky, right? So if
you look at the transcripts of the phone
calls from the passengers,
they describe a range of weapons.
>> Um, they're very unclear. Uh, we don't
know how long the blades were. Um, a
chemical weapon is described by one of
them. Um, but
that may have been a bluff. They they
they apparently showed a fake device uh
that was a bomb or a chemical weapon on
one of the flights. The reason why the
news coverage repeatedly said box
cutters is because box cutters, which
have a blade about this size and sitting
in a metal tube literally for opening
boxes, were specifically permitted to be
brought onto planes.
Um, and so the FAA to shield itself said
they used box cutters. We don't actually
know with box cutters
>> that they use blades of some kind,
>> but given the laxness of airport
security in the airports they chose and
especially Logan, these could be much
longer blades. Um, and they were able to
severely wound large angry adult
American men. Uh, so the blade would
have to be bigger than a box cutter. Um,
We just the the the answer is we just
don't know. But the box better thing was
a bureaucratic way to safeguard and silo
itself. The bureaucracy immediately
shifted into CIA
from the afternoon of the attacks
onward.
>> And no, go ahead.
>> Uh I was going to say and obviously
probably doesn't need to be said, but
they also had the element of surprise
once they were on the plane.
Yes. Yeah. There had been a long period,
decades in fact, before there since
there had been hijackings in the United
States. So, no one was expecting it.
>> Before we move on, you also mentioned
they'd rehearsed and practiced this
whole thing. What do we know about that?
>> Uh, so there is uh it's still
classified. Uh, but there is uh but I
have a copy. Uh, I probably should have
brought it. Um so the uh FBI um put
together a complete timeline based on
all of the movements of the hijackers
from the moment they arrived in the
United States to the moment they died.
Right? And to do that they put together
large amounts of data um
ATM receipts, restaurant receipts,
witnesses accounts, uh security cameras.
It's it's an incredible document, right?
>> Frankly, I almost thought about writing
a book just about that. Um, and in that
uh they would um there was a number of
they did scenario role playing where um
the guys who would be the muscle
practiced against the other guys if they
were unruly passengers. How would you
fight if they tackled you at the waist
or if they grabbed you from behind and
here's how you would throw them over
your head and so on and so on, right? Um
the
reports that Muhammad Ata had um planned
plan rehearsed in Iraq are
I think largely an internet rumor. It is
the case that the Iraqis had a Boeing
707 that they used to train other
terrorist groups uh before 911. Um the
idea of flying planes into buildings
goes back to um a document out of Iran
in 1987.
Um so the idea had been floating around
in jihadi circles for a while but it
does not appear that the 19 the
September 11th 19 hijackers on September
11th rehearsed in Iraq. So any internet
rumor to the side there's no evidence
for that. Be fascinating if we're true.
There's no evidence for that. But they
did rehearse in the United States in
various hotel rooms and in gyms uh
defending themselves. Um and they also
practiced uh what they would do uh how
they would take once they had the
cockpit, what they would do with the
aircraft, how they would level it off
and so on. And they also had quizzes,
written quizzes for each other as well.
And how did they practice the the actual
flying element? Did these flight
simulators or train?
>> Absolutely. Um and they did go to these
uh flight schools
uh where chillingly they said they
didn't know how to they didn't need to
learn how to take off or land. They just
needed to know how to operate the
aircraft in the air.
it I mean it it's just some of the stuff
I think particularly for our younger
audience you when you talk about airport
security or being able to smoke in the
cockpit or all of this stuff it must be
very hard to believe and the reason is
and coming on to to the consequences and
the aftermath
>> is that I Francis and I often talk about
this this where we we're both in our
early 40s I and we we have a lot of guys
in their 20s that work for
And we always talk about the fact that
we we think that nobody that generation
has any idea how different the world was
in the late 1990s. And I think 911 and
then the financial crash are the two
reasons for that. What was the impact
and the response and the aftermath?
We also don't understand the world that
the people in their 20s see because when
we see the same reality they see, we're
seeing it through the lens of 20 years
of experience and we may be putting
things into the wrong intellectual
categories, right? And they're able to
see it much more originally, right? So
this is always the generational problem
when you talk to people in their 70s and
80s and these World War II comparisons
because they're the children of World
War II survivors come up in their
conversation as a live thing the way
9/11 is for us. Right? So the years of
experience are a tool for insight but
they're also a tool for missing things.
Right? And um so
even when someone who's 20, someone
who's 40, someone who's 60 is looking at
the exact same object, they may see very
different things. And it's not because
the young people are dumb or the old
people
>> Oh, no. Not at all. Not at all. That's
not I certainly wasn't saying that
they're dumb.
>> This is this is human nature on for
better or for
>> Yeah, of course. What I was getting at
is the fact that the world changed very
profoundly and it seems to me
permanently and irreversibly
after 9/11. What was the immediate
reaction and the immediate aftermath of
this terrorist attack?
Homer wrote two of the most important
books in Western literature. The Odyssey
is the one that's had all the attention
recently. The Iliad, the one about
pride, rage, and leadership, which is
just as essential, now has a free course
from Hillsdale 2. Hillsdale College's
new free online course is taught by
Professor Steven Smith. It's not a
highlight reel, and it's not Homer for
beginners. It's a proper walk through
the text. Honor, courage, leadership,
friendship, sacrifice, and what it means
to live a noble life. You come away
understanding why Achilles real fight
isn't with the Trojans, is with himself.
This is one of more than 40 free courses
Hillsdale offers on the Constitution,
the Roman Republic, the American
founding, Genesis, the Second World War,
and more. All built the same way, taught
properly, and not dumb down. I couldn't
recommend Hillsdale courses more highly.
Go to hillsdale.edu/trigger
to enroll for free. That's
hillsdale.edu/trigger.
>> The most extraordinary thing happened in
America after 911. And this is going to
be
very hard for the people who didn't live
through it to remember to to believe but
it's true.
>> Uh the best way to ex to show this is uh
to tell you a quick story.
Um my father and mother were on the west
coast of the United States um to do a
book signing for my father and all
flights were cancelled. All flights were
grounded on 911 and didn't resume for a
long time. My father had the idea to
rent a car and drive back home to
upstate New York.
What is that about 5 and a half thousand
kilometers, six 3,000 miles, right? Uh
and it would take days because they
thought all the rental cars are going to
get booked up. We should grab it while
we can. And so they began this drive
across the United States in the hours
after September 11th.
And on lonely roads in Wyoming, he
saw these signs over and over again,
handmade signs, I love New York,
that had been hastily put together and
put up.
Wyoming is a deeply red state.
It does not surprise me when someone
from Wyoming says, "I never want to
visit Manhattan or the city of New
York." But yet we saw these signs
and in the highway overpasses in
Northern Virginia,
there were bed sheets with signs
written, you know, messages written on
them hanging over the side where you
could as you went down the superighway
read them. Messages of support and love.
Um an idea that politics should be put
aside. the country really came together
even though there were jet for the jet
fighter at least in New York and and
Washington jet fighters roaring overhead
um there was this idea that the country
should unify
um political speech moderated there was
a real coming together
and it everyone was afraid it wouldn't
last and of course it couldn't and it
didn't but it lasted far longer than you
would think and a lot of Americans
discovered
that they had more in common with each
other than they realized and even
families split aside by politics and
these are just anecdotal stories. I
don't have any statistical data, but
people reconnected and forgave each
other. And it was as horrible as the
loss of 3,000 people was.
Um,
the cultural impact
was not what commentators say today of
of fear and anger. That was part of it.
It was a desire to to write the wrongs.
And when Bush President Bush, uh, W.
Bush said in the crater that they were
still digging out at 911, the the World
Trade Center crater, he grabbed a
bullhorn from a construction worker.
And he says, "I hear you and the rest of
the world is going to hear from you very
soon.
>> Thank you.
>> I
want you all to know
We can't go any louder.
>> I want you all to know
>> that America today,
>> America today
is on bended knee in prayer for the
people whose lives were lost here. for
the workers who work here, for the
families who mourn. This nation stands
with the good people of New York City
and New Jersey and Connecticut
as we mourn the loss of thousands of our
citizens.
>> I can hear you.
>> I can hear you. The rest of the world
hears you. And the people
And the people who knocked these
buildings down will hear all of us soon.
USA
>> and
what the president didn't disclose is
the CIA paramilitary were already on
their way to Afghanistan
and they were reconnecting with the
Northern Alliance who they had funded in
the 80s remember separate from the
jihadis the Arab inquires
>> and you know there were personal
relationships
and um they began and setting up listing
posts and and forward advance areas and
coordinating with horse uh soldiers uh
and carrying out attack and within a few
weeks carrying out attacks against the
Taliban and against al-Qaeda.
Um, so the desire to eliminate an
al-Qaeda root and branch was definitely
there, but and maybe there's other data
that I'm not aware of, but I did not
there's not any evidence that I can see
that there was a profound hatred of
Muslims uh in the United States. Um,
at least after 911, the idea of America
being a profoundly racist country just
wasn't there. In fact, people
experienced the opposite.
uh unity, reconnection, and an
incredible resolve
to kill those who killed us.
>> And do you think that reaction
is exactly what Bin Laden wanted?
>> No. Uh if you read what I mean I can't
read his mind and he's dead but if you
read his documents the things he wrote
and the things he said he thought that
uh America was addicted to Coca-Cola
McDonald's was weak that he could
humiliate it as soon as he managed to
get US forces on the ground in
Afghanistan where they could fight them.
uh that they would defeat them,
humiliate them, and destroy America's
superpower status and triumph over them.
He thought he was pushing on a weak,
decadent society.
And he had many western academics he
could cite to support that mistaken
view.
>> But in fact, that is not western
society. It is not a society of decline.
It is a society in which its thinking
elite and some of its leadership have
lost confidence in it. But below the
elite level, it is still a high
functioning, confident society that
invents new things, that adapts quickly
to changes, and that is remarkably
understanding for people with people
different from themselves.
Um, I offered to when I was one of the
times in which I was in Iraq, I offered
to take uh my Kurdish translator and his
family to dinner.
>> He says, "Oh, let's have dinner at our
home." And so after eating dinner at
their home three or four times, like,
"No, let's let's pick the most expensive
restaurant and let's go there." Which
turned out to be a Chinese place. And as
we sit down, they are mystified by the
menu. Even though the place was a
kilometer from their home, they had
never been there. and he looks at me and
says,"Wh
would you eat other people's food?"
Western society is the opposite. It's
curiosity and w and openness to other
people's food, words, ideas,
perspectives.
And I don't think Bin Laden was
expecting the dynamism, the resolve, the
courage, innovation that Western
society, American society in particular,
was still able to muster and develop and
deploy with such a wallet.
>> And Richard, when you look and you watch
the footage from that day, it's so
shocking.
>> Yes. Whilst I was researching for this
interview, I, you know, was watching
documentaries and it was so horrific
just watching what was happening. I
didn't realize the emotional effect they
would have on me 25 years on. It must
have created such in many ways such a
deep psychological scar in the in the
American psyche.
>> Take two. Take two. And two, one. This
is as close as we can get to the base of
the World Trade Center. You can see the
firemen assembled here, the police
officers, FBI agents, and you can see
the two towers. A huge explosion now
raining debris on all of us. WE BETTER
GET OUT OF THE WAY.
HEY.
Oh my god.
That's right.
>> I'm just tired. I'm tired.
I don't have I don't have a radio.
>> The northwing.
>> Oh my god, there it goes.
You got me.
Get in. Here comes the hole. The cloud
is coming.
>> KEEP GOING. GO.
>> GET INSIDE.
>> It's going to jump right over this
building.
>> It's going to jump over the building.
>> In Washington. There has there is a
large fire at the Pentagon. The Pentagon
has been evacuated.
And there's you can see perhaps the
second tower, the front tower, the top
portion of which is collapsing.
Good Lord,
there are no words.
>> Yeah, I was watching a documentary on
the United 93 recently and I was
surprised. I was transported right back
in time. I was immediately angry um for
these hijackers who for their own
political goals
hijacked the lives of perfectly e decent
ordinary people and killed them for no
reason
>> and it just
injustice of that anger of that it put
it took me right back in time and I
understand why major media has been
afraid especially in the wake of 911 the
first five or 10 years they didn't
reshow those videos very often and only
and not for long and they didn't
documentaries and specials for five or
10 years and they were afraid of
arousing the great
angry dragon that is a US an American
sense of righteousness and anger
um for the sheer barbarity and unnecess
how unnecess necessary. It was um you
know, we all understand that as the
firemen go into the burning building to
save the children, some firemen may die.
We understand that when troops are
deployed, some may die.
But the loss of life for a political
drama in your head, completely
untethered from reality, coming from
a completely alien intellectual
ecosystem.
It's just beyond beyond understanding
for most Americans. The number one
question that came up in Google
searches, you know, weeks after 911 is
why do they hate us? Like we we don't we
don't even know who you are. Why do you
hate us? And it took Americans a long
time, and many don't understand this
yet.
They didn't understand us and come to
hate us.
They have a very rudimentary idea of who
we are.
It it was they had an ideological
vision in their head about what will
create um the final showdown between
themselves and the Americans in the
mountains of Afghanistan. And that was a
moment they
devoutly wanted to get to. and nothing
else mattered toward achieving that
bizarre goal. And I should probably say
a word here about al-Qaeda's um bin
Laden's statement to Americans about
Israel and Gaza and all this. That is
pure propaganda.
I I took a look at every al-Qaeda
statement and every bin statement before
al-Qaeda existed.
The references to Palestine, Gaza,
Israel, the West Bank, you can count on
one maybe two hands in a list of
nations. It's never singled out. It's
never been a focus.
Then that is one message to Americans
in which he is so clearly um reiterating
left-wing academics in in Western Europe
and the United States. uh and trying to
use this message to divide. It's it's
just enemy propaganda, right? It's
>> never an animating purpose. Um
you know, fun fact, some of the 911
hijackers had been Christian converts
into Muslim Islam. Uh one Zed Aljara, I
believe his name is, tried to leave the
plot. he his Lebanese girlfriend um who
was still Christian wanted to um to to
get married and and have him start a new
life and why don't you get away from
these crazy people and so he left and
Muhammad Ata had to go after him and
threaten him to get him to rejoin the
hijacking group. Right? Uh so
the real reasons have nothing to do with
bin Laden's statements about uh uh and
if you look at Zjara he says nothing
positively nothing about Gaza or West
Bank or the Palestinians not a single
word. So the idea this was an animating
principle of theirs is just not the
case. Uh there's a book by Dr. Aman
Alzar Huri which has been translated
into English. Uh he's he was the number
two person in al-Qaeda.
Um
and he the book is called Nights under
the prophet's banner.
I think you can read it online in
English for free. It's translated by the
Library of Congress from Arabic and it's
very revealing as to what gets what they
get into their animating principles. But
again, nothing about Gaza.
uh the their argument against the United
States is in in Nights the prophets's
banner and in several other texts is
very simple. They think the United
States is supporting the Arab
dictatorships that they suffer under
now. And so they blame the United States
for supporting dictators in uh or or
ruling class in Saudi Arabia and Egypt
and other places.
>> That's it. It's not a detailed critique
of American society. This is not the
democratic socialists uh right or the
Christian socialists in Western Europe,
right? This is not a detailed critique
of the market economy or US foreign
policy or anything like that. It is a
desire to create a new civilization in
the Arabic speaking world organized
along certain
uh eccentric religious ideas which you
can find and they've written them down
in the shade of the Quran is one
milestones both by you can find it under
nights of the prophet's banner go read
their literature if you want to
understand what drives them it's not
even Islam
I mean, Islam's at the surface, but you
dig into their ideology, it's deeply
influenced by Karl Marx and by Vladimir
Lenon. This is a fusion of Leninism and
Islamism, right? Or and Islam. And if
you read their works, it becomes
immediately clear that is the basis of
their thinking. it's not uh a particular
aspect of US or Western foreign policy.
>> And one of the
things that really impacted me when I
was watching these documentaries is the
recordings from the people on board the
planes to their families saying goodbye
to them for the last time.
And just the the the way that a lot of
these people just held it together and
were just very calm and were just
telling their family members how much
they loved them.
There's no words to describe it really.
I mean, you can try, but it's utterly
it's ultimately futile.
>> Hi, baby. I'm Baby, you have to listen
to me carefully. I'm on a plane that's
been hijacked. I'm on the plane. I'm
calling from the plane. want to tell you
I love you. Please tell my children that
I love them very much and I'm so sorry
babe. Um I don't know what to say.
There's three guys. They've hijacked a
plane. I'm trying to be calm. We're
turned around and I've heard that
there's planes that's been been flown
into the World Trade Center. I hope to
be able to see your face again. Baby, I
love you. Bye.
>> Elsa, it's Lynn. Um, I only have a
minute. I'm on United 93 and it's been
hijacked uh by terrorists who say they
have a bomb. Apparently, they uh have
flown a couple of planes into the World
Trade Center already and it looks like
they're going to take this one down as
well. Mostly I just wanted to say I love
you and I'm going to miss you
and and please give my love to my dad
and
honestly I just love you and I just
wanted to tell you that I don't know if
I'm going to get a chance to tell you
that again or not.
Um my and all my stuff is in the safe.
The uh the safe is in my closet in my
bedroom.
accommodation is you push C for clear
and then 0913
and then uh and then it should and maybe
pound and then it should unlock.
I love you and I hope I can talk to you
soon. Bye.
>> Jules, there's a sign uh on an airplane
that's been hijacked. If things don't go
well and it's not looking good, I just
want you to know I absolutely love you.
I want you to do good. So happy this
time. uh same to my parents and
everybody and I just totally love you
and uh I hope you
hi babe.
>> Yeah, one of the passengers on the
United 93
is talking to his wife and he says he
has to go because he's part of the plan
to retake the plane. She says, "Do you
want to talk to the children?" And he
says, "I'll talk to them tonight after
we land the plane.
absolute confidence their plan was going
to succeed.
>> Um but he had to project that confidence
because that was those are the last
words by which she was going to know him
and it was going to define who he was in
the mind of his wife and more
importantly in the minds of his children
for the rest of their days. He knew he
knew his chance of living was
slim.
But he had to project that confidence.
He had not to be he had to be a pillar
of strength and not wrinkle his inner
turmoil because he he had to steal
himself to take action, but he also had
to define himself in the minds of those
he loved.
And there are so many calls like that.
You're absolutely right, Francis. It's
it's heartbreaking. And you if you read
those transcripts, you end up admiring
those so-called people, the bravery
they could summon to be calm and
collected or appear this or appear to
calm and collected in the face of the
most extreme circumstances. It's
astonishing.
And as well it's obviously those people,
but it's also the emergency services,
the ambulance men, the police officers,
the fire officers. Just the fact that
these people ran into a burning
building, whether it was the towers,
whether it was the Pentagon when
everybody else was running away.
I mean, it's heroism of the highest
order.
I talked to Donald Rumsfeld a few weeks
after 911. He was the secretary of
defense
and
he mentioned that he had safely gotten
out of his office and how many people
had died on the Pentagon. And as he's
talking, he's moving his hands around
and finally I said, "Lar, show me your
hands." and he holds them up like this
and I could see burns
and he said, "Oh yeah, I was helping
remove the rubble before the security
dragged me away and I burned my hands."
Think about that. cabinet officer of the
United States joined everyone else at
the Pentagon in trying to dig out the
rubble to save people fighting for their
lives buried alive in hot burning bricks
twisted metal.
Uh, and the firemen who
not only went in to try to put out the
fire in the World Trade Center
came back out to exchange their oxygen
tubes
and then turned around and went back in.
That little moment of screwing in the
the fresh air, readjusting your mask,
wiping some sweat off the brow, and
turning around and going back in. That's
bravery. Turning around to go back into
danger to help others. It's these little
moments, these little snapshots
that define this day for me. Uh, I think
you suddenly realize that your country
is crowded with heroes wearing ordinary
faces.
And that's such a profound point because
in particularly nowadays in our culture,
the people who we celebrate,
I mean, it's it's pretty much tried to
say, but really shouldn't be celebrated.
the people whose words we listen to, you
think, do you have anything of value to
say? But you look at the people who are
actual are actual heroes. It's the
people who are ordinary men and women,
the firefighters, the fire officers, but
even the office workers. Some of the
stories of the office workers in on that
day are just remarkable. the people
turning around going to make sure that
every single person is out from their
particular office, making sure that
every that the corridors are clear and
sometimes these people just they simply
didn't make it out.
>> Yes.
Yeah. I mean, on 911, I was working for
the Wall Street Journal in Brussels and
my brother Brendan was working for the
Wall Street Journal in New York.
And my brother and I would talk multiple
times a day.
>> And
and like everybody else, all the phone
lines were jammed. Everyone was trying
to reassure themselves that their family
members were alive
and um the journal was in the World
Financial Center I believe at that time
right beside the Twin Towers
and um
Brendan was his phone
and
we couldn't reach him but we had the
journal we have these internal uh
communications
And then they begin evacuating the
building and they're reassembling the
team uh moving it by ferry to well
ultimately I think they went to
Princeton, New Jersey, but we were going
to have to put out the Wall Street
Journal that day from overseas. New York
was shut down and they're counting
heads, thousands of heads and the list
of missing Wall Street Journal people
gets smaller and smaller.
It's first it's hundreds, then it's
dozens,
and finally it's down to eight missing
people. And my brother is still on that
list.
And as I'm working with my colleagues in
Europe and Asia
to put out the paper that day
because New York was shut down, we had
to take over everything.
I was thinking to myself, is this have I
already had the last conversation with
my brother?
And I wish I could have said so many
things that I hadn't said because I was
thoughtless or
just not thinking about the gravity of
the situation.
And we end up working till
3:00 or 4 in the morning, Brussels time.
And um we're editing the official view
of the paper, the editorial,
and I'm about to go home and go to bed.
that beach comes through
and it's marked with my brother's name
and I'm like, "Oh my gosh, Brendan, is
that you?"
And he did not follow the evacuation
um with the other Wall Street Journal
staff.
He had usually he would take the 8:30
subway into lower Manhattan
and so he would have been inside the
World Trade Center looking to go up the
bridge and across to the World Financial
Center.
But he as he was about to get on the
train on the platform in Brooklyn, he
looked down and saw three spots of blood
on his shirt.
and he went home to change his shirt and
he got on the 845 subway which turned
out to be one of the last into lower
Manhattan that day
and he saw it all. He saw the second
plane.
He saw people jumping or falling from
the towers.
>> He was covered in the white dust as the
buildings collapsed. He walked across
the Brooklyn Bridge covered in sweat and
dust,
looking a bit like a ghost when he runs
into a journal colleague who is also
covered and who said to him, "Come with
me, Brendan. We're going to Bob's house.
We're going to put out the paper from
there." And so he never made any
official counts. He wasn't showing up in
the internal system because Bob's house
wasn't part of it.
Robert Hartley, the editor-in chief of
the Wall Street Journal and the editor
of the editorial page
and um
he um
he responds, "Yeah, of course it's me."
And I then I'm desperate to know how he
survived and what happened and whether
he's talked to any family members. No
one knew whether he was alive or not.
And um
many many people had that same
experience that day. Some didn't end as
happily as as mine did. And u
but this sudden eraser of lives for a
political cause
is so morally wrong.
Why people think politics in their head
justify harm to other people. always
amazes me.
>> Yes, Richard. Uh that is a very
worthwhile observation
um that applies I think more broadly to
just this particular incident. Um, we'll
we're going to uh continue the
conversation with our supporters on
Substack, but before we do, what do you
think is the one thing that people don't
talk enough about in relation to 9/11
that they really should?
>> Wow, so many things I could say to that.
Um,
one is to realize that
one, terrorism is not an Islamic
creation. Terrorism was invented in the
1830s
by a group of Russian radicals called
the Novemberists and the anarchists
around them. This is had been throughout
the 19th century a technique that the
Germans learned from the Russians.
Um in 1848 we see a lot of what we would
describe today as terrorist attacks. So
the idea that this is some defect in
Islam, no no it's something the Muslim
world learned from the Russians and the
Germans. Uh terrorism is not a natural
feature in Islam.
That's one thing. Second thing is
people join terrorist groups can be
radicalized by campus life like college
Muhammad. And we need to to pay much
more attention to how college life
structures the souls of the students who
pass through it in order to reduce this
conversion to radicalism. We can never
eliminate it, but we can sure reduce it.
And we're not really doing anything
serious about that. Third, how social
isolation
makes
um
a lot of terrorism possible by offering
it an endless supply of recruits.
Muhammad Ata, who was the the
operational commander of the 911
attacks,
was brought to um uh to to Hamburg,
Germany, who studied the Harvard
Technical School.
And he had a host family of social
democrats,
uh who were convicted, you know, just
have deep convictions of aggressive mind
view. They thought they were building a
stronger relationship between the West,
Germany in particular, and Egypt by
hosting him in their home. And they had
no skills to identify
that because he had gone through all
boys schooling. He found it very hard to
deal with German teenagers, girls of his
age because he had no social skills to
deal with it. and that as he started to
and they would take him to these Arab
events so he could feel more at home
and he's eventually identified by a
recruiter and his behavior begins to
change. He stops eating with the family,
insists on cooking his own food. He
wouldn't when he would watch television
with them, he would cover his eyes
whenever there would be an ad showing a
woman in a bikini or advertising some
Tunisian vacation or what have you. They
were not able to identify any of the
signs of increasing radicalization.
And
this sort of thoughtless dooodism really
needs to come with some training. How is
it the person you brought into your home
is gradually being radicalized by the
difference of himself and the new
society you thrust him into.
Sometimes pushing people before they're
ready into western society can be far
more radicalizing than leaving them at
home and giving them good books to read
in Egypt or someplace.
And it is not the case to know us to
love us. We westerners are deeply
strange people that are not like the
other people in the world. And that's we
could go on about what the differences
are. But when you're asking someone to
join that, don't think the answer is
going to be kumbaya. It could be I don't
fit in here and I hate you because I
don't fit in here and I'm willing to
join an ideology that will kill and ma
you to punish you for the way I feel
now. That is a very human response.
People become terrorists for human
reasons, not ideological ones. Ideology
is the cover, the excuse, the
rationalization.
Inside is a human being. And if you
don't change the mechanics that shape
those human beings, you will have
another September 11.
>> Richard, thank you so much for coming
back on and talking to us about such a
tremendously important event on its 25th
anniversary. Thank you all for watching
and listening. Please head over to
triggerpod.co.uk UK where Richard is
going to answer some of your questions.
What is your take on the fact that we
now have people with Islamic backgrounds
running from office for office in the US
who say America had it coming?